Mss.497.3.G41
American Philosophical Society
Miscellaneous collection on the American Indian, 1949-1961
Mss.497.3.G41
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Linear feet Ca. 365 items, 75 photographs
This collection pertains principally to the Cherokees of North Carolina and Oklahoma and to their language, ethnography, folklore, archeology, history, music, etc. Includes Indian studies and correspondence by Gillespie, notes on Indian dances and linguistics, bibliographies, publications of the Archaeological Society of Brigham Young University, and newspaper clippings. Also comprised of materials on: Apache, Calusa, Chippewa, Choctaw, Delaware, Eskimo, Fox, Iroquois, Karankawa, Kuchin, Louchens, Mattaponi, Muskogee, Navajo, Onondaga, Pueblo, Sauk, Seminole, Seneca, Shawnee, Sioux, Slave, Timucua, Tuscarora, Tutelo, and Wyandot. Contains: Gillespie, "A grammar of western dialect of Cherokee language of the Iroquoian family," 1949-1954 (131 pages); "Miscellaneous material on the Cherokee Indians and language"; "Miscellaneous items pertaining to the American Indian."
Ca. 365 items; 75 photographs.
Gillespie, John D.
Box 1-2
Scope and Contents note
"A grammar of western dialect of Cherokee language of the Iroquoian family": A discussion of the history of the Sequoyan syllabary; the western (North Carolina) Cherokee; migration; relation of syllabary characters to Cherokee design; phonemics and sound shifts as an indication of relation of Cherokee-Iroquoian to Caddoan languages; phonetics and morphophonemics; free forms vs. bound forms; grammar arranged by semantic categories.
"Miscellaneous material on the Cherokee Indians and language": Materials pertaining to the Western Cherokee Nighthawk Keetowahs, together with dance materials, music, medicinal and ceremonial observations, transcripts from notes, etc. (1951-1952). Includes Alice Marriott, Ethnographic observation of the nighthawk Keetowah, and Gillespie, The Kthula cult of Haiti.
Scope and Contents note
Native American Images note: Nearly 600 photomechanical prints, black and white silver gelatin photographs, ink and pencil sketches, maps, news clipping photographs, and color postcards of Eastern Cherokee Indians, collected and taken by John D. Gillespie while researching Native American music from 1947-1961. Images depict the social life and customs of the Cherokees of western North Carolina, eastern Tennessee and Oklahoma with such practices as ball playing, basket weaving, dances, beadwork, pottery and native dress. Also, some individual and group portraits of Junaluska, Sequoyah and Koshare Indian dancers. Includes some materials on Mayan, Cheyenne, Navajo, Choctaw, and Pueblo tribes. Referenced in the Supplement of the Freeman Guide to manuscripts relating to the American Indian.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by John D. Gillespie in honor of Dr. Frank Speck and accessioned, 02/1962. See in-house shelf list for additional accession numbers and dates.
Archaeological Society of Brigham Young University..; Junaluska, d.1858; Sequoyah, 1770?-1843; Cherokee dance; Cherokee Indians; Cherokee language; Cheyenne Indians; Choctaw Indians; Clippings.; Gelatin silver prints; Indian dance--North America; Indians of North America--Languages; Indians of North America--North Carolina; Indians of North America--Oklahoma; Indians of North America--Tennessee; Maps.; Navajo Indians; Newspaper clippings; Photomechanical prints; Photoprints.; Postcards; Pueblo Indians; Sketches.; Southeast Indians
- A grammar of western dialect of Cherokee language of the Iroquoian family, 1949-1954; No.1; Sequoyan syllabary; Gillespie, John D.
  Other Finding Aids note
  Freeman guide, #68 and 660. Film 1320
- Miscellaneous material on the Cherokee Indians, 1951-1962; No.2; Materials pertaining to the western Cherokee Nighthawk Keetowahs, together with dance materials, music, medicinal and ceremonial observations, transcripts from notes, etc. Including Alice Marriott "Ethnographic observation of the Nighthawk Keetowah" and John Gillespie "The Kthula cult of Haiti."; Gillespie, John D.
  Scope and Contents note
  Native American Images note: 9 pencil sketches, 1 negative print, 59 ink sketches, 6 newspaper clippings of diagrams of Keetouwah ceremonial dances, music score of a lullaby, glyphs of Kthulhu language of Haiti, and a Cherokee feast.
  Freeman guide, #69 and #605
- Eastern Cherokee reservation scrapbook, 1947-1954; No.3, item 1; Miscellaneous papers: scrapbook of photographs, newspaper clippings, picture postal cards, etc.; Gillespie, John D.
  Native American Images note: 38 black and white photographs, 6 color postcards, 24 newsclippings, 2 negatives of Cherokee individual portraits in native attire, weapons, dwellings, canoes, dances, basket weaving, and games in North Carolina and Tennessee.
  Freeman guide, #4010
  - Cherokee attire, 1947-1954
  - Cherokee man "chiefing", 1947-1954
  - Cherokee man with bear cub, 1947-1954
  - Cherokee men on stage, 1954
  - Cherokee utensils, 1947-1954
  - Commemoration of the Treaty of Dumplin Creek, 1954
- The Indian voice: Indian medium of expression, No.3, item 2
  Native American Images note: 49 photomechanical prints of portraits of Kiowa, Seminoles, Kaws, Cherokees.
- The Official guide to Cherokee, n.d.; No.3, item 3
  Native American Images note: 26 photomechanical prints of portraits, dwellings, pipes, moccasin.
- Junaluska, 1951; No.3, item 4
  Native American Images note: 6 ink sketches of portraits, cradle-board, grave sites, battle of horse-shoe bend, maps.
- Chief Junaluska, 1950; No.3, item 5
  Native American Images note: 6 ink sketches of photomechanical prints of portrait, boundary tree, ambush at Raven's place, Shawano war party, Wah-lah-see-yah.
- Miscellaneous papers: correspondence, 1950-1961; No.3, item 6; Gillespie, John D.
  Native American Images note: 18 ink sketches, 6 color postcards, 4 photomechanical prints of Zuni, Pueblo dwellings, relics, dancers and Cherokee dwelling, myth, portraits.
- Miscellaneous papers: newspaper clippings, photograph of clippings, notes, etc., 1953-1961; No.3, item 7; Gillespie, John D.
  Native American Images note: 9 newspaper photographs, 7 photomechanical prints of Cherokee portraits, artifacts, pipes, weapons, dwellings, grave sites.
- Miscellaneous papers: University archaeological society, Brigham Young University, No.3, item 8; Gillespie, John D.
  Native American Images note: 14 photomechanical prints of pottery, artifacts, stone carvings, Olmic stone head, archaelogical sites at Chiapas, Mexico.
- Miscellaneous papers: twenty-one articles on Indian dances, No.3, item 9; Gillespie, John D.
  Native American Images note: 9 photomechanical prints of Cheyenne dances; Cherokee stick ball; sand paintings in Navajo hogan.
- Miscellaneous papers: field notes on the North Carolina Cherokee, No.3, item 10; Gillespie, John D.
- Miscellaneous papers: Tahlequah, Oklahoma., 1930-1959; No.3, item 11; Gillespie, John D.
  Native American Images note: 5 photomechanical prints, 8 newsclipping photographs, 5 maps of Oklahoma Indian territory, Cherokee blankets, dwellings, settlements.
- Miscellaneous papers: bibliographies of American Indians, 1950; No.3, item 12; Gillespie, John D.
  Native American Images note: 24 newspaper clipping photographs from the New Cherokee Advocate of portraits, dwellings, cradleboards, utensils.
- Miscellaneous papers: Indian dances, No.3, item 13; Gillespie, John D.
  Native American Images note: 221 photomechanical prints of Koshare Indians artifacts, dances, native attire, portraits.
- Miscellaneous papers: studies on Indians, No.3, item 14; Gillespie, John D.
- Miscellaneous papers: American Indian linguistic studies, 1944-1947; No.3, item 15a; Gillespie, John D.
- Miscellaneous papers: American Indian liguistic studies, No.3, item 15b; Gillespie, John D.
- Miscellaneous papers: Cherokee linguistics, 1948-1950; No.3, item 16; Gillespie, John D.
- Miscellaneous papers: C.E.D.A.M. (Mexico) publications, 1960-1961; No.3, item 17; Gillespie, John D.
  Native American Images note: 15 photomechanical prints of artifacts, jewelry, skeletal remains, and pottery found in the sacred well of Chichen Itza.
- Miscellaneous papers: Indian studies, 1954-1960; No.3, item 18; Gillespie, John D.
  Native American Images note: 5 photomechanical prints from Sooner magazine of Native American paintings.
- Miscellaneous papers: Indian studies, 1948-1960; No.3, item 19; Gillespie, John D.
- Miscellaneous papers: Cherokee, N.C., 1952-1961; No.3, item 20; Gillespie, John D.
  Native American Images note: 10 color postcards, 63 photomechanical prints, 28 newspaper clipping photographs, 10 ink sketches of Cherokee Indian villages in North Carolina. Includes images of dwellings, dances, crafts, attire, ball playing, totems.
- Miscellaneous papers: Cherokee bibliography, n.d.; No.3, item 21; Gillespie, John D.